[{"question":"<p><strong>In the long run, all productive factors are<\/strong><\/p>","options":["fixed","semi-fixed","variable","semi-variable"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>Unemployment can be reduced by<\/strong><\/p>","options":["restricting the productive base of the economy","adopting capital intensive techniques of production","adopting labour intensive techniques of production","adopting a mixture of labour and capital-intensive technique of production"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>Elasticity of demand is an effective tool in the hands of a producer in that it enables him<\/strong><\/p>","options":["raise his profits and lower his cost","discourage buyers from cheating","determine what he will produce","set his price to maximize profit"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>Utility of commodity means<\/strong><\/p>","options":["its usefulness","power to satisfy a want","price of the commodity","satisfaction derived from the production of a commodity"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>By subsistence production we mean<\/strong><\/p>","options":["goods and services are produced for consumption only","goods and services are sold to others","raw materials are produced in the country","goods and services are produced for the market"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>Choice arises because?<\/strong><\/p>","options":["human wants are numerous but the resources needed to satisfy them are limited.","given numerous wants, only individuals and business make choices","the process of making a choice involves opportunity cost","an economist is not interested in the morality or otherwise of any choice made"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>Money becomes a very poor store of value in a period of<\/strong><\/p>","options":["deflation","stable prices","recession","inflation"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>The function of money as a standard of deferred payments _ _ _?<\/strong><\/p>\r\n<p>&nbsp;<\/p>","options":["makes it possible for an individual to build up stores of many things for future use","makes it possible for payments to be postponed from the present to a future date","facilitates the exchange of goods","makes easy calculation possible"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>By open market operations, we mean the process by which<\/strong><\/p>","options":["the Central Bank intervenes in the open market to buy or sell securities","the commercial banks intervene in the open market to buy or sell treasury bills","the money takes over the function of the Central bank","the bank rate is determined in the open market"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>Indirect taxes are taxes<\/strong><\/p>","options":["which are levied on the income and profits of individuals and firms","whose incidence always falls on the consumers","which are based on the progressive principle","which are levied on people and economic units through the goods and services they purchase"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>The situation whereby in a fiscal year a government's revenue receipts are less than its expenditure is referred to as<\/strong><\/p>","options":["budget deficit","balanced budget","budget surplus","unfavourable budget"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>Which of the following does not belong in respect of quality of money?<\/strong><\/p>","options":["durability","divisible into small units of value","portable","measure of value"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>Government budget can be described as the sum of<\/strong><\/p>","options":["indirect tax direct and loans expected within a financial year","planned recurrent expenditure and planned investment expenditure","planned capital expenditure for a development plan within a plan period","planned expenditure and expected revenue within a financial year"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>Malthus became known through his popular theory which may be stated simply as<\/strong><\/p>","options":["the death rate may become so high that people may not be able to produce","population may outgrow the means of subsistence","people will eventually decide not to have children","migration of people from one place to another may leave some parts of the world barren"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>Opportunity cost is a term which describes<\/strong><\/p>","options":["the initial cost of setting up a business venture","cost of one production in terms of forgone production of others","the monetary equivalent of utility of a commodity","cost related to an optimum level of production"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>Which of the following situation can give rise to economic problems<\/strong><\/p>","options":["unlimited human wants","wants of varying importance","limited means available for satisfying human wants","means used in different ways"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>Scale of preferences refers to<\/strong><\/p>","options":["consumers' preference for luxurious goods","the household monthly income","list of goods and services in order of priority","budget preparation without paying due regard to priority"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>The major objective of the current campaign for family planning in Nigeria is to<\/strong><\/p>","options":["reduce the death rate","limit the number of women a man can marry","keep the population growth rate constant","raise the standard of living of the population"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>The migration of young people from rural to urban areas in Nigeria should help to raise the<\/strong><\/p>","options":["standard of living in the urban areas","total productivity of labour in the rural areas","marginal productivity of labour in the rural areas","marginal productivity of labour in the urban areas"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>By definition, variable cost (VC) is related to total costs (TC) and fixed costs (FC) by the equation<\/strong><\/p>","options":["VC = TC + FC","VC = TC - FC","VC = TC \/ FC","VC = (TC)(FC)"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>The price mechanism is more effective in achieving efficient performance of the economy than the planning mechanism because of the<\/strong><\/p>","options":["role of supply and demand","role of material incentive","existence of buyers and sellers","role of money"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>A firm with marginal cost equal to the marginal revenue will produce the equilibrium if it is in<\/strong><\/p>","options":["purely competition only","pure monopoly only","monopolistic competition only","any type of market"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>The basic economic problems of the society include:<\/strong><\/p>","options":["what to produce, how and for whom","how to produce and sell","scarcity, when to produce and how","scarcity, for whom to produce and where"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>Opportunity cost is an economic concept which describes the?<\/strong><\/p>","options":["monetary equivalent of the utility of a commodity","amount of time or money invested on a commodity","sacrifice made for the satisfaction of a want","cost of retailing an optimum level of production of commodities"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>The necessity of choice is due to the fact that<\/strong><\/p>","options":["human wants are insatiable","consumers like to maximize satisfaction","resources are abundant","consumers are selective"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>Every economy requires accurate census because it assists in<\/strong><\/p>","options":["solving inflation problem","providing a sound framework for policy formulation","stimulating economic activities in the national economy","solving unemployment problem"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>The population of country X in 1990 was 35 million. The births were 450,000 while it recorded 210,000 deaths. If in the same year, its immigrants were 20,000 and 10,000 of its citizens left the country. Calculate the total population of the country at the end of 1990.<\/strong><\/p>","options":["24,250,000","25,350,000","34,750,000","35,250,000"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>Economics is a social science because it<\/strong><\/p>","options":["deals with an aspect of human behaviour","provides people with commodities they want","deals with limited resources which have alternative uses","deals with the production of scientific goods"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>Scarcity in Economics generally refers to?<\/strong><\/p>","options":["monopolization of limited resources","resources being limited","hoarding of goods","unavailability of essential goods in the market"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>Opportunity cost is defined as<\/strong><\/p>","options":["total cost of production","variable cost","money cost","real cost"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>A decision on what to produce is a problem of<\/strong><\/p>","options":["all economic systems","a mixed economic system only","a planned economic system only","a democratic socialist economic system only"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>The money payment made to owners of land and labour are<\/strong><\/p>","options":["rent and wages","interest and capital","wages and interest","dividend and salary"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>In economics, production is complete when<\/strong><\/p>","options":["goods are produced in the factories","goods and services reach the consumer","prices are fixed for goods and services","goods are sold to retailers"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>A society on its production possibility curve<\/strong><\/p>","options":["is using its resources efficiently but not fully","has attained full employment but not full production","is producing below capacity","has attained both full employment and full production"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>The system whereby goods are exchanged for goods is known as<\/strong><\/p>","options":["trade by exchange","trade by barter","stock exchange","cooperative society"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>Which of the following is a measure of central tendency<\/strong><\/p>","options":["percentage","variance","graph","median"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>The quantity supplied of books per week is represented by the equation <\/strong><strong><strong>Qs = 50 + 1\/4P<\/strong>. At a price of N16.00 the quantity supplied is<\/strong><\/p>","options":["45","65","54","56"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>Money becomes a very poor store of value in a period of<\/strong><\/p>","options":["deflation","inflation","stable prices","harvest"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>Money as a unit of account implies that it can be<\/strong><\/p>","options":["counted in units","used to facilitate exchange","used to measure the value of goods and services","used to store goods and services"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>A stock holder partakes of the profits of a limited liability business receiving<\/strong><\/p>","options":["shares","profits","wages and salaries","dividends"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>Near money is made up of<\/strong><\/p>","options":["very liquid assets which can easily be converted into money","currency and cash","fixed assets that cannot be converted into cash","the total money supply"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>Dividing change in total costs by change in quantity produced will lead to<\/strong><\/p>","options":["average total cost","marginal cost","average variable cost","average utility"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>The entire satisfaction that a consumer derives from a successive consumption of a particulat commodity is known as<\/strong><\/p>","options":["marginal utility","diminishing utility","average utility","total utility"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>The three broad categories of production are?<\/strong><\/p>","options":["direct, secondary and tertiary","primary, secondary and tertiary","primary, extractive and tertiary","agricultural, extractive and industrial"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>In a capitalist system, the means of production are owned by and controlled by&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["politicians","the government","private individuals","the workers"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>An economic good is described as a good which&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["yields utility and commands a price","is useful and occupies a space","increases the level of output of a firm","is found in only economic systems that are considered good"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>A production possibility curve shows<\/strong><\/p>","options":["how much of resources of society are used to produce a particular commodity","the rate of inflation","the rate of unemployment in the economy","the various combinations of two commodities that can be produced"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>The additional revenue obtained by using one or more unit of a factor is called its<\/strong><\/p>","options":["marginal product","additional product","marginal revenue product","average product"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>Given an original price N3.50 per kilogram of rice and a change in price of N1.40 and that the quantity purchased at the price is 10kg and a change in quantity of 5kg after the price change, the elasticity is equal to<\/strong><\/p>","options":["10.20","3.57","1.25","0.50"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>Which of the following is compatible with a firm in a purely competitive market?<\/strong><\/p>","options":["demand is inelastic","demand is infinitely elastic","marginal cost is falling","demand is greater than marginal cost"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>The difference between personal income and personal disposable income is<\/strong><\/p>","options":["personal income tax","investment income","personal savings","consumption expenditure"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>Capital consumption allowance refers to<\/strong><\/p>","options":["personal consumption expenditure","indirect business tax","depreciation of capital equipements","expenditure on capital equipment"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>One factor which influences the slope of a non-linear demand curve for a commodity is the<\/strong><\/p>","options":["price of the commodity","quantity of the commodity demanded","availability of substitutes","availability of complements"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>The Malthusian theory of population predicts that growth in food production will&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["keep pace with population growth","be at a faster rate than population growth","be at a slower rate than population growth","be more rapid than population growth in the developing countries"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>In estimating the national income of a country, the three approaches usually adopted are the<\/strong><\/p>","options":["expenditure, value-added and output","income, final product and output","expenditure income and output","avoidance of double counting, final expenditure and value-added"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>The group of unemployed members of a community who are physically handicapped or disabled is generally classified under unemployment as<\/strong><\/p>","options":["frictional","cyclical","residual","hidden"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>The difference between visible exports and visible imports of a country in monetary terms is known as&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["balance of trade","balance of payments","terms of trade","foreign reserves"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>The main economic goal of ECOWAS is the attainment of&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["regional free trade","multilateral trade","bilateral trade","economic self-reliance"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>The equilibrium market price is determined at a point where<\/strong><\/p>","options":["consumer can buy all they desire","sellers can dispose all their wares","the price is moderate","quantity consumers desire equals quantity sellers offer"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>Taxes which are levied on a person's expenditures are known as<\/strong><\/p>","options":["purchase tax","sales tax","direct tax","income tax"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>The following are the functions of Central bank of Nigeria except<\/strong><\/p>","options":["bankers of last resort","issuing of coins and paper money","bankers to the government","accept time deposits by customers"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>Utility derived from consumption of a commodity can be measured by&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>\r\n<p>&nbsp;<\/p>","options":["weight of the commodity","volume of the commodity","value of the commodity","price of the commodity"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>The long-run is defined as the period when<\/strong><\/p>","options":["some factors of production are not fixed","all factors of production can be varied","all factors of production are fixed","some factors of production are not available"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>Money becomes a good store of value in a period of&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["stable price","inflation","depression","deflation"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>A tax rate that grows at the same time with income is called<\/strong><\/p>","options":["company tax","regressive tax","income tax","proportional tax"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>All of the following are market structure except<\/strong><\/p>","options":["pure competition","monopolist competition","monopoly","distribution"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>When a consumer's satisfaction decrease as he\/she consume more of commodity, the commodity is responding to<\/strong><\/p>","options":["law of diminishing marginal utility","constant marginal utility of money","rationality","increase in income"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>A monopolist can determine either price of commodity or<\/strong><\/p>\r\n<p>&nbsp;<\/p>","options":["the colour","the quantity","the volume","content"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>Which of the following can be described as a primary product<\/strong><\/p>","options":["a television set","school bag","a barrel of crude oil","a note book"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>A common problem with using value-added method in measuring National Income is<\/strong><\/p>","options":["collation of prices","increase in price","double counting","reduction in prices"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>Inflation caused by increasing price of inputs is called<\/strong><\/p>","options":["hyper-inflation","demand-pull inflation","cost-push inflation","creeping inflation"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>Commercial banks can create money in the following ways<\/strong><\/p>\r\n<p>&nbsp;<\/p>","options":["by issuing coin and paper money","by borrowing money from banks abroad","by receiving deposits from individuals","by printing more money"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>The price of a commodity is determined by the<\/strong><\/p>","options":["supplier","quantity of good demanded","interact of demand and supply","quantity of goods supplied"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>Government expenditure and revenue are divided broadly into<\/strong><\/p>","options":["good and bad","recurrent and capital","federal and state","statutory and current"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>The index for measuring economy welfare out of the following is&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["gross domestic product","gross capital information","per capital income","disposable income"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>The number of people who are qualified to work and who offer themselves for employment are called<\/strong><\/p>\r\n<p>&nbsp;<\/p>","options":["migrant labour","working population","labour turnover","working class"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>When the general price level persistently falls, the rate of unemployment&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["rises","falls proportionately","stagnates","equals natural growth rate"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>To ensure high employment rates, developing countries should<\/strong><\/p>","options":["build more universities","protect infant industries","organize trade fairs","allow more foreigners"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>The act of selling goods in foreign markets at prices below those charged at home markets is called<\/strong><\/p>","options":["exchange","dumping","exporting","specialization"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>To achieve an equilibrium position, the consumer must buy so much of each commodity whose price is equal to its<\/strong><\/p>\r\n<p>&nbsp;<\/p>","options":["average utility","marginal utility","total utility","declining utility"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>The transfer of ownership of a public enterprise to individuals and firms is called<\/strong><\/p>","options":["take over","acquisition","commercialization","privatization"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>Mr. Daramola's income is N80,000 per month while that of Mr. Olutoki's is N120,000 per month. If Messrs Daramola and Olutoki pay N9,000 and N12,000 respectively as taxes, the tax system is<\/strong><\/p>","options":["progressive","proportional","regressive","retrogressive"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>The theory of comparative cost advantage is associated with<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Alfred Marshal","Adam Smith","David Ricardo","J.B. Say"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>The economic community of West Africa is an example of&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["economic integration","multilateral trade","international competition","regional marketing board"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>An essential characteristic of a market economy is<\/strong><\/p>","options":["government control","consumer sovereignty","producer surplus","lower price"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>Which of the following is not an objective of the Organization of Petroleum Exporting Countries(OPEC)&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["stabilization of oil prices","co-ordination of oil price","ensuring steady supply of oil","stagnation of developed economies"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>When the value of a nation's exports is greater than its imports<\/strong><\/p>","options":["a favourable balance of trade exist","the net foreign trade is zero","inflation occurs","unfavourable balance of trade exists"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>An economy which exhibits features of both private and state enterprises is known as<\/strong><\/p>","options":["mixed economy","capitalist economy","socialist economy","modern economy"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>Public expenditures on education and health is known as expenditure on<\/strong><\/p>","options":["general services","commercial services","economic services","social services"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>A normal demand curve<\/strong><\/p>","options":["is concave to the point of origin","convex to the point of origin","parallel to X axis","slopes down from left to right"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>When the demand for a commodity is inelastic, total revenue will fall if?<\/strong><\/p>","options":["price is increased","price is reduced","price remain constant","price is not given"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>An economic system in which most capital goods produced are owned by individuals and private firms is known as<\/strong><\/p>","options":["mixed economy","planned economy","capitalist economy","traditional economy"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>Which of these best describes the Malthusian Theory of population?<\/strong><\/p>","options":["increase in population census hunger and death","the population increases faster than food supply","the necessity of birth control","population growth is desirable for development"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>Which of the following is most liquid asset to a commercial bank?<\/strong><\/p>","options":["money at call and short notice","treasury bill","commercial bill","cash"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>The coefficient of price elasticity of demand is zero when demand is<\/strong><\/p>","options":["fairly elastic","perfectly inelastic","fairly inelastic","unitary elastic"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>The term marginal propensity to consume can be best explained as the&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["desire to spend more income on consumption","change in consumption as percentage of the change in income","average income regularly spent on consumption","total expenditure on consumption"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>Demand in economics is synonymous with<\/strong><\/p>","options":["needs","wants of the consumers","all goods demanded in the market","want supported with ability to pay"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>The price and quantity of crude oil sold to other countries by Nigeria is fixed by the<\/strong><\/p>","options":["ECOWAS","IMFC","OPEC","NNPC"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>Which of the following statement is not true of cheque?<\/strong><\/p>","options":["produce an alternative to carrying large sum of money around","can be written out for any amount of money needed","are legal tender","provide a form of receipt"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>Which of the following are determinants of the rate of population growth?<\/strong><\/p>","options":["birth rate, immigration and death rate","birth rate, death rate and emigration","death rate, birth rate and net migration","immigration, large families and birth rate"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>Distribution involves the<\/strong><\/p>","options":["movement of raw materials to production centre","transfer of goods and services from one market to another","movement of goods and services by middle men to urban centre","transfer of goods and services from production centre to consumers"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>Which of the following is not a member of OPEC?<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Indonesia","Iran","Venezuela","Egypt"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>Scarcity in Economics means that resources<\/strong><\/p>","options":["are not enough to share among the producers of goods and services","needed to satisfy human wants that are limited","are never enough to share among consumers of goods and services","required to meet our essential wants are limited"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>Which of the following is regarded as fixed cost?<\/strong><\/p>","options":["cost of raw material","cost of fuel","cost of light","rent on land"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>The primary objective of the Agricultural Credit Guarantee Scheme is the provision of&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["guarantee for loans granted by banks for agricultural purposes","agricultural inputs to facilitate credit from banks","agricultural products for consumers","loans for every farmer"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>The magnitude of the national income of a country depends on all the following except the<\/strong><\/p>","options":["quantity of natural resources available","level of technical know-how","mobility of labour","level of productivity"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>The National Growth rate of population is the<\/strong><\/p>","options":["sum of the birth rate and the death rate","sum of the birth rate and the net migration rate","birth rate minus the death rate","birth rate divided by the net migration"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>Marginal cost curve intersects average cost curve<\/strong><\/p>","options":["from above at its lowest point","from below before the lowest point","from below at its lowest point","from below after the lowest point"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>In an inflationary period which of the following statements is NOT true?<\/strong><\/p>","options":["wages rise simultaneously with prices","the purchasing power of money diminishes","more money runs after a limited quantity of goods","money supply increases"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>Public expenditure creates expansionary effects in the economy when it is<\/strong><\/p>","options":["in excess of government revenue","channeled into capital projects","diverted into imports","financed through oil revenue"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>Comparative cost doctrine of international trade means specialization in production<\/strong><\/p>","options":["according to absolute cost advantages","according to absolute cost disadvantages","according to comparative cost advantages","on the basis of the availability of labour"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>The meaning of 'dumping' is selling goods in foreign market<\/strong><\/p>","options":["at a price below that received in the home market","at a price higher than that received in the home market","at a price equal to the cost price in the home market","in order to encourage the indigenous producers"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>Disequilibrium in the balance of payments means<\/strong><\/p>","options":["imports of the country exceeding its exports","overall deficit or surplus in the current account and capital account of the balance of payments","capital flowing out of the country exceeds the capital flowing into the country","deficit in the trade balance"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>One main quality of a good is that it<\/strong><\/p>","options":["is sold in the market","satisfies wants","is made in the factory","is always tangible"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>The amount of labour a producer hires relative to other factor inputs depends on the?<\/strong><\/p>","options":["price of labour or its wages","price of labour, machinery and other inputs","price of machinery","price of other inputs"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>Warehousing facilities in the distribution and marketing of products are provided by<\/strong><\/p>\r\n<p>&nbsp;<\/p>","options":["manufacturers","wholesalers","retailers","consumers"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>A firm is said to be a public joint-stock company when it<\/strong><\/p>","options":["is owned by the government","is operated as a public corporation","is operated in a non-democratic fashion","sells shares to members of the public and publishes its account"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>Which&nbsp; of the following is not among the canons of taxation as set out by Adam Smith<\/strong><\/p>","options":["equality","security","certainty","convenience"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>How many National Development plans did Nigeria have between 1960 and 1984?<\/strong><\/p>","options":["one","two","four","five"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>When total revenue is at a maximum, marginal revenue is<\/strong><\/p>","options":["constant","negative","zero","positive"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>Foreign exchange control in Nigeria is administered by the<\/strong><\/p>","options":["United Bank of Africa","Union Bank of Nigeria","First Bank of Nigeria","Central Bank of Nigeria"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>At every point of an indifference curve, the<\/strong><\/p>","options":["total utility is decreasing","prices of all goods are constant","consumer is satisfied","level of utility is constant"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>In a firm three employees earn N5,500.00 each, four earn N3,300.00 each, two earns N5,000.00 each and one earns N7,000.00, the mean income of the employee is<\/strong><\/p>","options":["N5,200.00","N4,760.00","N4,670.00","N2,080.00"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2015"}]